Guide to the Reserve Officers Training Corps, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Reserve Officers Training Corps, Yale University, records
1917-1972
RU 599
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
The records consist of correspondence, reports, memoranda, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia documenting the activities and operations of the Army and Navy Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) at Yale.
Yale University. Reserve Officers' Training Corps
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 42-A (YRG 42-A), Records of military training programs at Yale.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by type of material.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Battery was the first Army training program established at Yale in 1915. Eventually Yale had four batteries which became the Connecticut 10th Field Artillery of the National Guard. In 1916, Yale replaced its batteries with the Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) and the Yale Naval Training Unit (originally the Motor Boat Patrol and later known as NROTC). In the spring of 1918, existing ROTC programs were suspended and replaced with the Student Army Training Corps (SATC). The program was designed to establish military training units in colleges and to substitute specialized military training for the normal curriculum during World War I. Students were subject to military regulations and the existing ROTC programs (Army and Naval) were coordinated by the SATC. The SATC was demobilized by Congress in 1918. The ROTC programs were re-established at Yale in 1919.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of correspondence, reports, memoranda, photographs, newspaper clippings, and memorabilia documenting the activities and operations of the Army and Navy Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) at Yale.
Soldiers -- Education, Non-military -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Administration; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; United States. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps; Yale University. Reserve Officers' Training Corps
- Materials concerning military training programs, 1917-1972; Accession 1971-A-005
  - Correspondence, Reports, Memoranda
    - Administrative file, 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report to the President and notes, correspondence, memoranda, 1929-1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Biographies (officers), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Campbell, William: concerning British invasion of New Haven, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cannon and Castle Military Honor Society
      - Certificates (blank), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Charter, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1948-1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Current membership rosters, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Financial, 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Meetings and activities, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Membership, 1947-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Records, 1928-1962 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Superceeded Charter, 1932-1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Enrollment Report, 1921-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14 - 15)
    - History, organizational, 1916-1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - History: ROTC at Yale, 1963-1972 (Box 3, Folder 17 - 18)
    - Instructor memoranda, field orders, and notes of Chauncey P. Williams, Jr., from ROTC camp at Edgwood Arsenal, MD, 1922 (Box 3, Folder 18a)
    - National student league, circa 1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Polo fund, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - ROTC News, undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Separation Policy, Army Air Force, 1949-1967 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Unit Journal, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Yale ROTC pamphlets, 1927-1952 (Box 3, Folder 24 - 25)
  - Photographs
    - Commissioning, 1968-1970 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Drills and parades, undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - East Haven Rifle Range, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 27A)
    - Military Ball, 1959? (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Military Ball, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Negatives, 1959
      - Col. Brown (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Col. Brown, Capt. Arnold and Major Day (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Col. Brown, Major Eblen, Major Day and Capt. Arnold (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Outstanding Student Award, 1955-1961 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Summer Camp
      - Ft. Benning, Georgia, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Ft. Devens, Massachusetts, 1957-1962 (Box 4, Folder 33-37)
      - Ft. Knox, Kentucky, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 38)
      - Ft. Lewis, Washington, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 39)
      - Ft. Meade, Maryland, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 40)
      - Ft. Sill, Oklahoma, 1953-1955 (Box 4, Folder 41)
      - Summer Camp (unidentified), undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
      - Camp activities, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Ceremonies, presidential review,campus, staff, 1925-1970 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Class pictures, 1960-1968 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Miscellaneous, 1950-1969 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Memorabilia
    - Duty Roster, officers, 1946-1963 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - National Conference of Civilian Aides, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 48)
    - National Guard, Connecticut Tenth Field Artillery, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 49)
    - Newspaper clippings, memoranda, polo score sheet and clippings, 1919-1927 (Box 6, Folder 50)
    - Clippings, 1946-1953 (Box 6, Folder 51)
    - Releases, 1948-1967 (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
    - Yale Daily News, 1954-1961 (Box 7, Folder 54-55)
    - Military Science and Tactics, Department of, 1955-1959 (Box 7, Folder 56)
    - Clippings, 1955-1961 (Box 7, Folder 57)
    - Policy books: to assist instructors in course and administrative procedure, 1948-1951 (Box 8, Folder 58-59)
    - Summer Camp: Fort Devens, Massachusetts (booklet), 1960 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Summer Camp: Fort Belvoir, Virginia (booklet), 1961 (Box 8, Folder 61)